<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="/main.xsl"?>
<b:blog xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" xmlns:b="http://blog.othree.net"  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://blog.othree.net http://blog.othree.net/blooog.xsd">
	<b:blogTitle>O3noBLOG</b:blogTitle>
	<b:blogDescription></b:blogDescription>
	<b:entries>
		<b:entriesMeta>
			<b:listType>s</b:listType>
			<b:listData listID="000885" baseName="data-on-web-best-practice">網路發佈資料之最佳實踐</b:listData>

			<b:previous>
				<b:mTitle>2016</b:mTitle>
				<b:mDate>2017-02-17</b:mDate>
				<b:mBase>2016</b:mBase>
			</b:previous>


			<b:next>
				<b:mTitle>Visual Studio Code Copy with Syntax Highlighting</b:mTitle>
				<b:mDate>2017-03-02</b:mDate>
				<b:mBase>vscode-copy-with-syntax</b:mBase>
			</b:next>

		</b:entriesMeta>
		<b:entry entryID="000885" baseName="data-on-web-best-practice">
			<b:author>
				<b:authorName>othree</b:authorName>
				<b:authorEmail>othree@gmail.com</b:authorEmail>
				<b:authorUrl></b:authorUrl>
			</b:author>
			<b:datetime>
				<b:date>2017-03-01</b:date>
				<b:time>00:02:14</b:time>
			</b:datetime>
			<b:category>web</b:category>

			<b:CommentsAccepted>0</b:CommentsAccepted>


			<b:PingsAccepted>0</b:PingsAccepted>

			<b:title>網路發佈資料之最佳實踐</b:title>
			<b:content>
				<b:summary> 前幾天 W3C 發佈了這份文件 Data on the Web Best Practices （DWBP），內容是關於在網路上發佈資料時的最佳實踐（公開或非公開的都適用），讓我想到了之前的 g0v summit 羅佩琪分享提到的一個重點，開放是有成本的，當時演講的影片： 稍微看過這份文件後，覺得之前確實蠻缺乏這份整理好的文件，每點看了就都覺得，確實是應該要這樣的，不過沒有這種整理好的 checklist 其實真的要做的時候還蠻容易漏東漏西的，然後就是，每一點都是成本啊！！ 整份文件還蠻有翻譯的價值的，比較不像是 HTML Spec 會常常更新，不過我自然沒這麼多時間可以翻譯，所以就先把重點標題翻起來放，以後有人要開始就先有個基礎了，DWBP 整份文件有 35 點 Best Practice，每一點都有標題、簡述、原因、預期結果、可能實做方法、如何測試、證據、好處、範例等內容，其中好處的部分是分成八種： Comprehension，人類容易理解理解 Processability，可程式自動處理 Discoverability，可讓程式自動發現 Reuse，容易重複使用 Trust，可靠 Linkability，可連結 Access，容易存取 Interoperability，容易互動（發佈者和使用者之間） 我只翻譯了其中的標題和簡述，順便附上每一點的好處（上面的八種好處），以下就是這 35 點 Best Practice：...</b:summary>
				<b:mainContent><p><a class="thumbnail" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/othree/32951614622/" title="Data on the Web Best Practices by othree, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm3.staticflickr.com/2901/32951614622_395e8d1b32_b.jpg" width="1024" height="576" alt="Data on the Web Best Practices" srcset="https://farm3.staticflickr.com/2901/32951614622_395e8d1b32_b.jpg 1024w" /></a></p>

<p>前幾天 W3C 發佈了這份文件 <a href="https://www.w3.org/TR/dwbp/">Data on the Web Best Practices</a> （DWBP），內容是關於在網路上發佈資料時的最佳實踐（公開或非公開的都適用），讓我想到了之前的 g0v summit 羅佩琪分享提到的一個重點，開放是有成本的，當時演講的影片：</p>

<div class="embed_16_9">
<iframe width="853" height="480" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/aIuHcEmKZ2I" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen="allowfullscreen"></iframe>
</div>

<p>稍微看過這份文件後，覺得之前確實蠻缺乏這份整理好的文件，每點看了就都覺得，確實是應該要這樣的，不過沒有這種整理好的 checklist 其實真的要做的時候還蠻容易漏東漏西的，然後就是，每一點都是成本啊！！</p>

<p>整份文件還蠻有翻譯的價值的，比較不像是 HTML Spec 會常常更新，不過我自然沒這麼多時間可以翻譯，所以就先把重點標題翻起來放，以後有人要開始就先有個基礎了，DWBP 整份文件有 35 點 Best Practice，每一點都有標題、簡述、原因、預期結果、可能實做方法、如何測試、證據、好處、範例等內容，其中好處的部分是分成八種：</p>

<ul>
<li>Comprehension，人類容易理解理解</li>
<li>Processability，可程式自動處理</li>
<li>Discoverability，可讓程式自動發現</li>
<li>Reuse，容易重複使用</li>
<li>Trust，可靠</li>
<li>Linkability，可連結</li>
<li>Access，容易存取</li>
<li>Interoperability，容易互動（發佈者和使用者之間）</li>
</ul>

<p>我只翻譯了其中的標題和簡述，順便附上每一點的好處（上面的八種好處），以下就是這 35 點 Best Practice：</p>
</b:mainContent>
				<b:extendContent><ul>
<li>Metadata <br />
詮釋資料
<ul>
<li>Provide metadata <br />
提供詮釋資料(metadata) <br />
Provide metadata for both human users and computer applications. <br />
提供可讓人類閱讀和程式可處理的詮釋資料 <br />
優點：R, C, D, P</li>
<li>Provide descriptive metadata <br />
提供資料介紹的詮釋資料 <br />
Provide metadata that describes the overall features of datasets and distributions. <br />
提供介紹資料集整體特性和發佈資訊的詮釋資料 <br />
優點：R, C, D</li>
<li>Provide structural metadata <br />
提供資料結構的詮釋資料 <br />
Provide metadata that describes the schema and internal structure of a distribution. <br />
每次發佈都提供資料綱要(schema)和資料結構的詮釋資料 <br />
優點：R, C, P</li>
</ul></li>
<li>Data Licenses <br />
資料授權
<ul>
<li>Provide data license information <br />
提供資料授權的資訊 <br />
Provide a link to or copy of the license agreement that controls use of the data. <br />
提供鏈節到資料所使用授權的協議文件 <br />
優點：R, T</li>
</ul></li>
<li>Data Provenance <br />
資料發佈者
<ul>
<li>Provide data provenance information <br />
提供資料發佈者的訊息 <br />
Provide complete information about the origins of the data and any changes you have made. <br />
提供完整的資料發佈者的訊息以及所有的修改紀錄 <br />
優點：R, C, T</li>
</ul></li>
<li>Data Quality <br />
資料品質
<ul>
<li>Provide data quality information <br />
提供資料品質資訊 <br />
Provide information about data quality and fitness for particular purposes. <br />
提供資料針對特定用途的品質和適應性資訊 <br />
優點：R, T</li>
</ul></li>
<li>Data Versioning <br />
資料版本
<ul>
<li>Provide a version indicator <br />
提供明確版本號 <br />
Assign and indicate a version number or date for each dataset. <br />
提供每個資料集的明確版本號或是發佈日期 <br />
優點：R, T</li>
<li>Provide version history <br />
提供版本歷史 <br />
Provide a complete version history that explains the changes made in each version. <br />
提供完整的版本歷史，說明每個版本的變動 <br />
優點：R, T</li>
</ul></li>
<li>Data Identifiers <br />
資料識別符
<ul>
<li>Use persistent URIs as identifiers of datasets <br />
使用固定的 URI 作為資料集的識別符(identifier) <br />
Identify each dataset by a carefully chosen, persistent URI. <br />
為每個資料集都謹慎的挑選一個永久固定的 URI 作為識別用 <br />
優點：R, L, D, I</li>
<li>Use persistent URIs as identifiers within datasets <br />
在資料集之間使用 URI 做為連結的識別符 <br />
Reuse other people's URIs as identifiers within datasets where possible. <br />
連結其它資料集時，盡可能使用其它資料集既存的 URI 作為資料集之間連結的識別符 <br />
優點：R, L, D, I</li>
<li>Assign URIs to dataset versions and series <br />
提供特定版本和最新版本的的識別用 URI <br />
Assign URIs to individual versions of datasets as well as to the overall series. <br />
每個版本都提供一個獨立的識別用 URI，整個系列的資料也要提供一個特定的識別 URI <br />
優點：R, D, T</li>
</ul></li>
<li>Data Formats <br />
資料格式
<ul>
<li>Use machine-readable standardized data formats <br />
使用程式可處理的標準格式 <br />
Make data available in a machine-readable, standardized data format that is well suited to its intended or potential use. <br />
提供程式可處理的標準資料格式，並且是適合資料預期及潛在應用的格式 <br />
優點：R, P</li>
<li>Use locale-neutral data representations <br />
使用非地區性的資料表現形式 <br />
Use locale-neutral data structures and values, or, where that is not possible, provide metadata about the locale used by data values. <br />
使用非地區性的資料結構和形式，否則需提供所使用資料形式的詮釋資料 <br />
優點：R, C</li>
<li>Provide data in multiple formats <br />
提供多種格式 <br />
Make data available in multiple formats when more than one format suits its intended or potential use. <br />
如果資料預期及潛在的應用有不只一種適合的格式，則都提供 <br />
優點：R, P</li>
</ul></li>
<li>Data Vocabularies <br />
資料詞彙
<ul>
<li>Reuse vocabularies, preferably standardized ones <br />
盡量重複使用詞彙，並優先使用標準有定義的詞彙 <br />
Use terms from shared vocabularies, preferably standardized ones, to encode data and metadata. <br />
在資料本體和詮釋資料中，盡量使用已經有人使用的詞彙，並優先使用標準有定義的詞彙 <br />
優點：R, P, C, T, I</li>
<li>Choose the right formalization level <br />
選擇正確的數據尺度 <br />
Opt for a level of formal semantics that fits both data and the most likely applications. <br />
為資料挑選一個適當的尺度，以符合資料本身的意義和它最可能的應用 <br />
優點：R, C, I</li>
</ul></li>
<li>Data Access <br />
資料取得
<ul>
<li>Provide bulk download <br />
提供打包下載 <br />
Enable consumers to retrieve the full dataset with a single request. <br />
讓使用者可以只用一個請求就取得全部的資料集 <br />
優點：R, A</li>
<li>Provide Subsets for Large Datasets <br />
大資料集要單獨提供子集 <br />
If your dataset is large, enable users and applications to readily work with useful subsets of your data. <br />
如果你的資料集很大，讓使用者可以針對他的應用只下載一部分的子集 <br />
優點：R, L, A, P</li>
<li>Use content negotiation for serving data available in multiple formats <br />
使用內容協商機制來決定提供的資料格式 <br />
Use content negotiation in addition to file extensions for serving data available in multiple formats. <br />
除了副檔名之外，還可以使用 HTTP 的內容協商機制來決定提供的資料格式 <br />
優點：R, A</li>
<li>Provide real-time access <br />
提供及時的存取 <br />
When data is produced in real time, make it available on the Web in real time or near real-time. <br />
如果資料是即時產生的，也提供可以取得即時資料的方法 <br />
優點：R, A</li>
<li>Provide data up to date <br />
提供最新版的資料 <br />
Make data available in an up-to-date manner, and make the update frequency explicit. <br />
總是提供到最新版本的資料，並且固定更新的頻率 <br />
優點：R, A</li>
<li>Provide an explanation for data that is not available <br />
無法提供的資料要說明原因 <br />
For data that is not available, provide an explanation about how the data can be accessed and who can access it. <br />
針對無法直接提供的資料，說明如何取得及誰可以取得 <br />
優點：R, T</li>
<li>Make data available through an API <br />
讓資料可以透過 API 取得 <br />
Offer an API to serve data if you have the resources to do so. <br />
如果有足夠的資源，提供 API 服務來供應資料 <br />
優點：R, P, I, A</li>
<li>Use Web Standards as the foundation of APIs <br />
使用網路標準作為 API 的基礎 <br />
When designing APIs, use an architectural style that is founded on the technologies of the Web itself. <br />
設計 API 服務時，使用網路基礎的技術作為架構核心 <br />
優點：R, L, I, D, A, P</li>
<li>Provide complete documentation for your API <br />
提供完整的 API 文件 <br />
Provide complete information on the Web about your API. Update documentation as you add features or make changes. <br />
在網路上提供完整的 API 文件，並且在 API 有更新時即時更新文件 <br />
優點：R, T</li>
<li>Avoid Breaking Changes to Your API <br />
避免 API 有不向前相容的變動 <br />
Avoid changes to your API that break client code, and communicate any changes in your API to your developers when evolution happens. <br />
避免重大的 API 更新造成應用端程式錯誤，更改 API 時都要跟開發人員溝通 <br />
優點：T, I</li>
</ul></li>
<li>Data Preservation <br />
資料保存
<ul>
<li>Preserve identifiers <br />
保留識別符 <br />
When removing data from the Web, preserve the identifier and provide information about the archived resource. <br />
當從網路上移除資料時，保留該資料的識別符，並且提供該資料歸檔保存的資訊 <br />
優點：R, T</li>
<li>Assess dataset coverage <br />
評估資料集覆蓋率 <br />
Assess the coverage of a dataset prior to its preservation. <br />
評估資料集的覆蓋率來做為歸檔保存時的參考 <br />
優點：R, T</li>
</ul></li>
<li>Feedback <br />
回饋
<ul>
<li>Gather feedback from data consumers <br />
從資料使用者收集回饋意見 <br />
Provide a readily discoverable means for consumers to offer feedback. <br />
提供一個容易發現的方式讓使用者提供意見回饋 <br />
優點：R, C, T</li>
<li>Make feedback available <br />
公開回饋意見 <br />
Make consumer feedback about datasets and distributions publicly available. <br />
公開使用者對資料集和發佈方式的回饋意見 <br />
優點：R, T</li>
</ul></li>
<li>Data Enrichment <br />
加強資料
<ul>
<li>Enrich data by generating new data <br />
增加新資料來加強現有資料集 <br />
Enrich your data by generating new data when doing so will enhance its value. <br />
當新資料可以提升資料集的價值時，就著手產生新資料 <br />
優點：R, C, T, P</li>
<li>Provide Complementary Presentations <br />
提供補充的內容來展示資料 <br />
Enrich data by presenting it in complementary, immediately informative ways, such as visualizations, tables, Web applications, or summaries. <br />
提供資料的各種用例，像是視覺化呈現、表格、網路應用程式或是摘要等來讓資料更多元 <br />
優點：R, C, A, T</li>
</ul></li>
<li>Republication <br />
再散佈
<ul>
<li>Provide Feedback to the Original Publisher <br />
提供回饋意見給原發佈者 <br />
Let the original publisher know when you are reusing their data. If you find an error or have suggestions or compliments, let them know. <br />
讓資料的原發佈者資料你有再利用他的資料，如果有發現任何錯誤或可以改進的地方，也讓他知道 <br />
優點：R, I, T</li>
<li>Follow Licensing Terms <br />
遵照授權條款 <br />
Find and follow the licensing requirements from the original publisher of the dataset. <br />
確認原始發佈資料集的授權條款，並遵守之 <br />
優點：R, T</li>
<li>Cite the Original Publication <br />
標註原發佈者 <br />
Acknowledge the source of your data in metadata. If you provide a user interface, include the citation visibly in the interface. <br />
在詮釋資料內標註資料來源，如果有建立使用者介面，也要在上面顯示資料來源 <br />
優點：R, D, T</li>
</ul></li>
</ul>

<p>翻譯可能有問題，Patch Welcome。最後附上一些翻譯時參考的資料：</p>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://w3c-html-ig-zh.github.io/w3c-glossary/">https://w3c-html-ig-zh.github.io/w3c-glossary/</a>  </li>
<li><a href="http://terms.naer.edu.tw/">http://terms.naer.edu.tw/</a></li>
<li><a href="http://www.lac.org.tw/law/documents/02/06231.pdf">http://www.lac.org.tw/law/documents/02/06231.pdf</a></li>
</ul>
</b:extendContent>
			</b:content>
			<b:comments commentCount="0">

			</b:comments>
			<b:trackbacks trackbackCount="0" trackbackURL="">

			</b:trackbacks>
		</b:entry>
	</b:entries>
</b:blog>